Register of the Taisiia Anatol'evna Bazhenova Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Taisiia Anatol'evna Bazhenova papers,
1915-1978
2001C28
Hoover Institution Archives
7 microfilm reels (0.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, clippings, and photographs, relating to Russian literature and Russian émigré affairs.
Bazhenova, Taisiia Anatol'evna
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biographical Note
Taissiia Anatol'evna Bazhenova, 1900-1978
T. A. Bazhenova was born on 17 May 1900 into a literary family: her father, Anatolii Dmitrievich Bazhenov, was, among other things, editor of the journal Irtysh, published by the administration of the Siberian Cossacks during the Russian Civil War. It was during the Civil War, in 1918, that T. A. Bazhenova published her first work: a poem in the Omsk newspaper Zaria. On arrival in Harbin in 1920, she became a correspondent of the newspapers Russkii golos and Zaria, and also served on the staff of the Society for the Study of Manchuria (Obshchestvo izucheniia Man'chzhurskogo kraia). Upon marrying Aleksandr Stepanovich Postnikov, she assumed his last name, but generally continued to publish her writings under her maiden name. Taisiia Anatol'evna Bazhenova.
In the United States, she was a correspondent for most of the major Russian newspapers on the West coast, also contributing articles, poems, short stories, and other pieces to journals and anthologies. Many of these are represented in the collection. Her newspaper articles primarily reflected émigré life, and included interviews with actors, writers, singers, and others.
Scope and Content Note
T. A. Bazhenova was a journalist and writer who wrote short stories and newspaper columns on a variety of subjects, mostly concerned with émigré life (sometimes under the pseudonyms Nina Krasovskaia (N. K.), N. Rusanov, and Miss Li). The collection contains many of her writings, as well as collected materials (almost exclusively clippings) on émigrés and their activities (apparently as background material for her own writings and interviews). Also of interest is her correspondence with various literary and cultural figures, particularly Russian poets in China.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
China.; Russia.; Russian literature.; Russians--China.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1922-1978 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clippings, family file, identity paper, poems and scrapbook, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Clippings about or mentioning T. A. Bazhenova (Folder 1: 1)
  - Family file
    - Bazhenov, Anatolii Dmitrievich (father)
      - Death notice (Folder 1: 2)
      - Writings (newspaper columns) (Folder 1: 3)
    - Bazhenova, Evdokiia Ivanovna (mother). (Folder 1: 4)
      Death notices
    - Postnikov, Aleksandr Stepanovich (husband). (Folder 1: 5)
      Obituaries and death notices
  - Identity paper (Folder 1: 6)
  - Poems dedicated to T. A. Bazhenova (Folder 1: 7)
  - Scrapbook. (Folder 1: 8)
    Includes clippings of newspaper articles by or about her, and by and about her father, A. D. Bazhenov. Also includes some correspondence and photographs
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 9)
- Correspondence, 1915-1974 (Box 1)
  Letters, cards, and attachments, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Includes letters addressed to A. D. Bazhenov and A. S. Postnikov. See also Biographical File/Scrapbook
  - General, 1925-1955 and undated (Folder 1: 10)
    Includes congratulatory letters on the 25th anniversary of her journalistic career, 1943
  - Unidentified, 1915-1945 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
  - Achair, Aleksei (Gryzov, Aleksei Alekseevich), 1927-1936 (Folder 1: 12)
    Includes attached poems
  - Berezovskii, E. P., 1925-1941 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Beta, Boris (Butkevich, Boris), []., 1924 or 1925 (Folder 1: 14)
    General note
    See also Photographs for his likeness
    Includes attached poems.
  - Bibinov, M. S., 1934-1945 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Borzov, Nikolai, 1934-1935 and undated (Folder 1: 16)
  - Butkevich, Boris.
    See Beta, Boris
  - Dolgushkin, E. G., 1952 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Eliseev, F., 1969 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Grebenshchikov, Georgii and Tat'iana, fragment, 1960 and undated (Folder 1: 19)
  - Gryzov, Aleksei Alekseevich.
    See Achair, Aleksei
  - Gryzov, Aleksei G., 1925-1932 (Folder 1: 20)
    See also Subject File/Cossacks--Siberia
  - Guins, George C., 1943 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Highgate Road Social Science Research Station, Berkeley, California, 1971 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Ivanov, Vsevolod, 1924 (Folder 1: 23)
    Includes attached poem
  - Kal', Aleksei, 1937 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Kolosova, Marianna, 1935 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Kulaeva, G., 1948 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Malozemova, Elizaveta, 1934 and undated (Folder 1: 27)
  - Mazurova, A., 1946 and undated (Folder 1: 28)
  - Mitropol'skii, A.
    See Nesmelov, Arsenii
  - Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, California, 1949 and undated (Folder 1: 29)
  - Naumenko, V., 1974 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Nesmelov, Arsenii (Mitropol'skii, A.), 1935 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Okulich, Iosif Konstantinovich, 1946 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Ostroumov, Boris Vasil'evich, 1925 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Serebrennikova, A., 1973 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Shcherbakov, Mikhail Vasil'evich, 1934-1935 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Shul'gin, Pavel, 1943-1944 and undated (Folder 1: 36)
  - Sten, Anna, 1935 and undated (Folder 1: 37)
    See also Biographical File/Scrapbook for additional letter and Subject File/Sten, Anna
  - Sudakov, Aleksandr, 1942 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Volkova, Mariia, 1939 and undated (Folder 1: 39)
  - Zharov, Sergei, 1937 (Folder 1: 40)
- Speeches and Writings, 1919-1956 and undated (Box 2-3)
  Newspaper columns, poetry, and short stories, arranged chronologically by title. See also Biographical File/Scrapbook
  - General
    - Newspaper columns, 1920-1956 and undated
      Includes reviews, news coverage, and other brief matter. Lengthy and serialized pieces are arranged by title below
      - Holographs (Folder 2: 1)
      - Typescripts. (Folder 2: 2)
        Many items are untitled and/or fragmented
      - Printed copies
        - Undated (Folder 2: 3)
        - 1920-1940 (Folder 2: 4)
        - 1941-1956 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Poetry, 1919-1943 and undated (Folder 2: 6)
      Holograph, typescript and printed copies
    - Short stories. (Box-folder 3: 1)
      Primarily untitled fragments. Holograph and typescript
  - "Amerikanskaia soldatka,", n.d. (Folder 3: 2)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Apriel',", n.d. (Folder 3: 3)
    Typescript
  - "Chuzhoi bereg,", n.d. (Folder 3: 4)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Diadiushka Karakhana,"., n.d. (Folder 3: 5)
    Holograph
  - "Kharbin - San Frantsisko,", n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
    Printed copy
  - "Kuma,", n.d. (Folder 3: 7)
  - "Na sopkakh Man'chzhurii,", n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Rozhdestvenskie obychai,", n.d. (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Shkola Santa Klausov,", n.d. (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Siennoi bazar,", n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
  - Story of pre-Revolutionary Russian army life, n.d. (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Vesna v revoliutsiiu," Viestnik Obshchestva russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny, n.d. (Folder 3: 13)
  - "Zelenyi abazhur,", n.d. (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Intimnost',"., 1924 April 27 (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Stantsiia Oloviannaia," Viestnik Obshchestva russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny, and Feniks, 1934 September 1935 September 15 (Folder 3: 16)
    Holograph and printed copy
- Subject File, 1919-1978 (Box 3-6)
  Clippings and letter, arranged alphabetically by subject
  - Actors--Russia (Folder 3: 17)
  - Air pilots--Russia (Folder 3: 18)
  - Artists--Russia (Folder 3: 19)
  - Ballet dancers--Russia (Folder 3: 20)
  - Brynner, Yul (Folder 3: 21)
  - Cherkasskii, Aleksei (Folder 4: 1)
  - Choirs (Music)--Russia (Folder 4: 2)
  - Composers--Russia (Folder 4: 3)
  - Cossacks
    - General (Folder 4: 4)
    - Siberia (Folder 4: 5)
  - Displaced persons (Folder 4: 6)
  - Don Cossack Chorus (Conductor: Serge Jaroff) (Folder 4: 7)
  - Dukhobors (Folder 4: 8)
  - General Platoff Don Cossack Chorus. (Folder 4: 9)
    Includes letter from Rostislav Petrov to G. T. Sukhov, editor of Novaia zaria, 1940
  - Kurenko, Mariia (Folder 4: 10)
  - Mamoulian, Rouben (Folder 4: 11)
  - Orchestra conductors--Russia (Folder 4: 12)
  - Pianists--Russia (Folder 4: 13)
  - Romanov family. (Folder 4: 14)
    Includes clippings on émigré Romanovs and on various pretenders to the throne
  - Russian literature (Folder 4: 15)
  - Russian poetry. (Box-folder 5: 1)
    Includes a prose poem by Anton Sorokin entitled Simfoniia revoliutsii (Omsk, 1919)
  - Russians--California--San Francisco (Folder 5: 2-3)
  - Russians--China (Folder 5: 4)
  - Russians--Philippines (Folder 5: 5)
  - Russians--United States (Folder 5: 6)
  - Russkaia Osvoboditel'naia Armiia (Folder 5: 7)
  - Russkaia Osvoboditel'naia Armiia (Folder 5: 8)
  - Scientists--Russia (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Shaliapin, Fedor (Folder 6: 2)
  - Singers--Russia (Folder 6: 3)
  - Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Sten, Anna (Folder 6: 5)
  - Wood, Natalie (Folder 6: 6)
  - World War, --Peace., 1939-1945 (Folder 6: 7)
    Materials relating to the activities of Soviet delegates at the San Francisco Conference, 1951
  - Miscellany (Folder 6: 8-10)
- Photographs, n.d. (Folder 6: 11)
  Sixteen negatives and eighteen prints depicting Taisiia Bazhenova, Aleksandr Postnikov, Boris Beta, Sikorskii aircraft and miscellaneous other people, places and things